ILGWU. Local publications, 5780/195 PUBS
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
ILGWU. Local publications
1935-1948.
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
5780/195 PUBS
1 cubic feet
1 linear foot
Publications
Contains issues of The Emancipator, which began as the publication of local 187 in 1936; became the publication of locals 187, local 188, and local 273 in 1938; and eventually the publication of the Milwaukee Joint Board (locals 187, 188, 273, 292, and 334). In addition to coverage of Milwaukee and national news, The Emancipator covered other Wisconsin locals: Raincoat Makers' Union 374 (La Cross, then later, Wausau), Cotton Dress Makers' Union 379 (La Crosse), Garments Workers' Unions 381 (Chippewa), Raincoat Makers Union 322 (Milwaukee?), Sportswear Union 325 (Baraboo), Cotton Dress Workers 417 (Watertown), Knitgoods Workers' Union 432 (Delevan), Underwear Workers' Union 450 (New London), Sportswear (later Raincoat) Workers Union 464 (Stoughton), Sportswear Workers Union 503 (Stoughton), Cotton Dress Workers' Union 508 (Mauston).
6325039
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff
Date completed:
March 2011
EAD encoding:
Cheryl Beredo, March 2011
Biographical / Historical
The International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union was founded in New York City in 1900 by mostly Socialist immigrant workers who sought to unite the various crafts in the growing women's garment industry. The union soon reflected changes in the sector and rapidly organized thousands of unskilled and semi-skilled women, mostly Jewish and Italian young immigrants. Exemplifying the "new unionism," the ILGWU led two of the most widespread and best-known industrial strikes of the early Twentieth Century: the shirtwaist makers' strike of 1909 in New York City and the cloak makers' strike of 1910 in Chicago. The union also tried to adapt to the fragmented and unstable nature of the industry. It adopted the "protocol of peace," a system of industrial relations that attempted to ensure stability and limit strikes and production disruption by providing for an arbitration system to resolve disputes.
The ILGWU exemplified the European-style social unionism of its founding members. They pursued bread and butter issues but provided educational opportunities, benefits, and social programs to union members as well. In 1919, the ILGWU became the first American union to negotiate an unemployment compensation fund that was contributed to by its employers. The ILGWU also pioneered in the establishment of an extremely progressive health care program for its members which included not only regional Union Health Centers but also a resort for union workers, known as Unity House. The Union also had an imaginative and pioneering Education Department which not only trained workers in traditional union techniques, but provided courses in citizenship and the English language.
David Dubinsky, an immigrant from Belarus who came to the US in 1911, provided strong leadership that led to unprecedented growth in the union during his presidency from 1932 to 1966. He led the union through successful internal anti-communist struggles, built on the ascendancy of industrial unionism by encouraging the formation of the Committee for Industrial Organization, and helped the union become an important political force in New York City and state politics, and in the national Democratic Party and Liberal Party as well.
In the period following the Second World War, the union suffered a decline in membership as manufacturers avoided unionization and took advantage of less expensive labor by moving shops from the urban centers in the northeast to the south, and later abroad. The ethnic and racial character of the ILGWU also changed as European immigrants were supplanted by Asians, Latin Americans, African- Americans, and immigrants from the Caribbean.
In July 1995 the ILGWU merged with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union (ACTWU) at a joint convention, forming UNITE (Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees). At the time the new union had a membership of about 250,000 in the United States, Canada, and Puerto Rico.
Biographical / Historical
Local 187 of the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union (ILGWU), also known as the Raincoat Workers' Union, was based in Milwaukee, Wisconsin. Also based in Milwaukee, Wisconsin were: Local 188 of the ILGWU, also known as the Cotton Dress Workers' Union; Local 273, also known as the Lingerie and Undergarment Workers' Union; Local 292, also known as the Knitworkers' Union; and Local 334, also known as the Dressmakers' and Alteration Workers Union.
Scope and Contents
Contains issues of The Emancipator, which began as the publication of local 187 in 1936; became the publication of locals 187, local 188, and local 273 in 1938; and eventually the publication of the Milwaukee Joint Board (locals 187, 188, 273, 292, and 334). In addition to coverage of Milwaukee and national news, The Emancipator covered other Wisconsin locals: Raincoat Makers' Union 374 (La Cross, then later, Wausau), Cotton Dress Makers' Union 379 (La Crosse), Garments Workers' Unions 381 (Chippewa), Raincoat Makers Union 322 (Milwaukee?), Sportswear Union 325 (Baraboo), Cotton Dress Workers 417 (Watertown), Knitgoods Workers' Union 432 (Delevan), Underwear Workers' Union 450 (New London), Sportswear (later Raincoat) Workers Union 464 (Stoughton), Sportswear Workers Union 503 (Stoughton), Cotton Dress Workers' Union 508 (Mauston).
Conditions Governing Access
The ILGWU Records, except for publications and materials produced for publication, are restricted. Materials created prior to twenty years from the current date are open to researchers only with prior written permission from the Director of the Kheel Center; materials created during the past twenty-years are closed; the minutes of the General Executive Board are closed. For more information contact the Kheel Center.
Related Materials
5780. ILGWU Records
5780 PUBS. ILGWU. Publications
General
"Permanent deposit."
Women's clothing industry -- New York (State) -- New York; Women's clothing industry -- United States; Clothing workers -- Labor unions -- New York (State) -- New York; Clothing workers -- Labor unions -- United States; Clothing workers -- New York (State) -- New York; Clothing workers -- United States; Industrial relations -- New York (State) -- New York; Industrial relations -- United States; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. Local 187; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. Local 188; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. Local 187; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. Local 188
6325039
- The Emancipator, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  September - October
- The Emancipator, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  November - December
- The Emancipator, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  January - February
- The Emancipator, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  March - April
- The Emancipator, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  May - June
- The Emancipator, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  July - August
- The Emancipator, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- The Emancipator, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- The Emancipator, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- The Emancipator, 1938-1939 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- The Emancipator, 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- The Emancipator, 1942-1943 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- The Emancipator, 1944-1948 (Box 1, Folder 13)